planning.center 2018-09-05

# Planning Center Privacy Policy

We collect user information in a manner consistent with the laws of the countries in which we do business. When a user registers for any of the Services we must ask for information such as the user’s name, company name, email address, billing address, and/or credit card information. If you created a new account with us, you will have been asked to check a box indicating your agreement to provide this data in order to use our services. This consent provides us with the legal basis we require under applicable law to process your data. You maintain the right to withdraw such consent at any time. If you do not agree to our use of your personal data in line with this policy, please do not use our services. 

As is true of most websites, we gather certain information automatically. This information may include Internet protocol (IP) addresses, browser type, Internet service provider (ISP), referring/exit pages, the files viewed on our site (e.g., HTML pages, graphics, etc.), operating system, date/time stamp, and/or clickstream data to analyze trends in the aggregate and administer the site. 

We use collected information for the following general purposes: products and services provision, billing, identification and authentication, services improvement, contact, and research. The information we collect is used to improve the content and quality of the Services. User information is not shared with or sold to other organizations for commercial purposes, except to provide products or services the user has requested, when the user has given us permission to share such information. This policy is not intended to place any limits on what we do with data that is aggregated and/or de-identified so it is no longer associated with an identifiable user. 

We may share your information with third parties who provide services on our behalf to help with our business activities. These companies are authorized to use your personal information only as necessary to provide these services to us. These services may include: 

  * Fulfilling orders and delivering packages 
  * Payment processing 
  * Providing customer service 
  * Sending marketing communications 
  * Fulfilling subscription services 
  * Conducting research and analysis 
  * Providing cloud computing infrastructure 

A list of these third parties, along with a way to subscribe to updates, is available at <https://planning.center/subprocessors/>. 

In certain situations, Ministry Centered Technologies may be required to disclose personal data in response to lawful requests by public authorities, including to meet national security or law enforcement requirements. We may also disclose your personal information as required by law, such as to comply with a subpoena or other legal process, when we believe in good faith that disclosure is necessary to protect our rights, protect your safety or the safety of others, investigate fraud, or respond to a government request. 

We do not use your personal data for the purposes of automated decision-making. However, we may do so in order to fulfill obligations imposed by law, in which case we will inform you of any such processing and provide you with an opportunity to object. 

In the event of a change in ownership, or a direct merger or acquisition with another entity, Ministry Centered Technologies reserves the right to transfer all of our user information to a separate entity. In this event, we will notify our users when user information is transferred and becomes subject to a different privacy policy. 

Ministry Centered Technologies and its partners use cookies or similar technologies to analyze trends, administer the website, track users’ movements around the website, and to gather demographic information about our user base as a whole. You can control the use of cookies at the individual browser level, but if you choose to disable cookies, it may limit your use of certain features or functions on our website or service. 

A cookie is a small amount of data, which often includes an anonymous unique identifier, that is sent to the user’s browser from a web site’s computers and stored on the user’s computer hard drive. 

Our Services use the following types of cookies for the purposes set out below: 

###  Essential Cookies 

These cookies are essential to provide you with services available through our Services and to enable you to use some of its features. For example, they allow you to log in to secure areas of our Services. Without these cookies, the services that you have asked for cannot be provided, and we only use these cookies to provide you with those services. 

###  Functionality Cookies 

These cookies allow our Services to remember choices you make when you use the Services, such as remembering your login details and remembering the changes you make to other parts of the Services. The purpose of these cookies is to provide you with a more personal experience and to avoid you having to re-enter your preferences every time you visit the Services. 

###  Analytics and Performance Cookies 

These cookies are used to collect information about traffic to our Services and how users use our Services. The information gathered does not identify any individual visitor. The information is aggregated and anonymous. It includes the number of visitors to our Services, the websites that referred them to our Services, the pages they visited on our Services, what time of day they visited our Services, whether they have visited our Services before, and other similar information. 

We use this information to help operate Services more efficiently, to gather broad demographic information and to monitor the level of activity on the Services. 

We use Google Analytics and other third party analytics services for this purpose. Google Analytics uses its own cookies. It is only used to improve how our Services work. You can find out more information about Google Analytics cookies [here.](https://developers.google.com/analytics/resources/concepts/gaConceptsCookies)

You can find out more about how Google protects your data [here.](http://www.google.com/analytics/learn/privacy.html)

You can prevent the use of Google Analytics relating to your use of our Services by downloading and installing the browser plugin available [here.](http://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=en-GB)

###  Targeted and Advertising Cookies 

We partner with a third party to either display advertising on our website or to manage our advertising on other sites. Our third-party partner may use technologies such as cookies to gather information about your activities on this website and other sites in order to provide you advertising based upon your browsing activities and interests. If you wish to not have this information used for the purpose of serving you interest-based ads, you may opt out by clicking [here](http://preferences-mgr.truste.com/) (or if located in the European Union click [here](http://www.youronlinechoices.eu/) ). Please note this does not opt you out of being served ads. You will continue to receive generic ads. 

###  Social Media Cookies 

These cookies are used when you share information using a social media sharing button or “like” button on our Services or you link your account or engage with our content on or through a social networking website such as Facebook, Twitter, or Google+. The social network will record that you have done this. 

If you wish to subscribe to our newsletter(s), we will use your name and email address to send the newsletter to you. You may choose to stop receiving our newsletter or marketing emails by following the unsubscribe instructions included in these emails, or you can contact us at [support@planning.center.](mailto:support@planning.center)

Upon request Ministry Centered Technologies will provide you with information about whether we hold any of your personal information. You may access, correct, or request deletion of your personal information by contacting us at [support@planning.center.](mailto:support@planning.center) We will respond to your request within a reasonable timeframe. In certain circumstances we may be required by law to retain your personal information, or may need to retain your personal information in order to continue providing a service. 

If your personal information changes, or if you no longer desire our service, you may make changes by clicking on the Accounts link in global navigation bar at the top of the screen. If you are a customer of one of our Clients and have a data access, correction, or deletion request, please see the section on “Client and Data Storage”. 

The security of your personal information is important to us. We follow generally accepted standards to protect the personal information submitted to us, both during transmission and once it is received. You can read more about our security practices [here.](https://planning.center/security/) If you have any questions about the security of your personal information, you can contact us at [security@planning.center.](mailto:security@planning.center)

We may retain your information for as long as your account is active or as needed to provide you services, comply with our legal obligations, resolve disputes and enforce our agreements. 

If a breach of data occurs within our services, we will notify you via a notification posted within the services and via an email notification at your last listed email address within 30 business days of discovering the breach. By using our services, you acknowledge and agree that we may send you electronic notifications via email in lieu of notifications by mail. If you would still like to receive notifications by mail, you can let us know by contacting us at [support@planning.center](mailto:support@planning.center) or  866-726-2730. 

We collect information under the direction of our Clients, and have no direct relationship with the individuals whose personal data we process. If you are a customer of one of our Clients and would no longer like to be contacted by one of our Clients that use our service, please contact the Client that you interact with directly. We may transfer personal information to companies that help us provide our service. Transfers to subsequent third parties are covered by the service agreements with our Clients. 

You have the right to access your personal information, however we have no direct relationship with the individuals whose personal data we process. An individual who seeks access, or who seeks to correct, amend, or delete inaccurate data should direct his or her query to the Ministry Centered Technologies Client (the data controller). If requested to remove data we will respond within a reasonable timeframe. 

Although we own the data storage, databases and all rights to the Planning Center application, our users retain all rights to their data. We will never sell or share user client data with any third parties, or contact the user’s clients directly. We also will not utilize user data in our database to compete with our users, market to our users’ clients, or advertise or contact our users’ clients for any other means of profit. We respect the privacy of our users, and the privacy of our user’s client data. 

We will retain personal data we process on behalf of our Clients for as long as needed to provide services to our Client. Ministry Centered Technologies will retain this personal information as necessary to comply with our legal obligations, resolve disputes, and enforce our agreements. 

When you download and use our Services, we automatically collect information on the type of device you use and operating system version. 

We use mobile analytics software to allow us to better understand the functionality of our Mobile Software on your phone. This software may record information such as how often you use the application, the events that occur within the application, aggregated usage, performance data, and where the application was downloaded from. We do not link the information we store within the analytics software to any personally identifiable information you submit within the mobile application. 

Ministry Centered Technologies participates in and has certified its compliance with the EU-U.S. Privacy Shield Framework and the Swiss-U.S. Privacy Shield Framework. We are committed to subjecting all personal data received from European Union (EU) member countries and Switzerland, respectively, in reliance on each Privacy Shield Frameworks, to the Framework’s applicable Principles. To learn more about the Privacy Shield Frameworks, and to view our certification, visit the [U.S. Department of Commerce’s Privacy Shield List.](https://www.privacyshield.gov/)

Ministry Centered Technologies is responsible for the processing of personal data it receives, under each Privacy Shield Framework, and subsequently transfers to a third party acting as an agent on its behalf. Ministry Centered Technologies complies with the Privacy Shield Principles for all onward transfers of personal data from the EU and Switzerland, including the onward transfer liability provisions. 

With respect to personal data received or transferred pursuant to the Privacy Shield Frameworks, Ministry Centered Technologies is subject to the regulatory enforcement powers of the U.S. Federal Trade Commission. In certain situations, we may be required to disclose personal data in response to lawful requests by public authorities, including to meet national security or law enforcement requirements. 

If you have an unresolved privacy or data use concern that we have not addressed satisfactorily, please contact our U.S.-based third party [dispute resolution provider](https://feedback-form.truste.com/watchdog/request) (free of charge). 

Under certain conditions, more fully described on the [Privacy Shield website,](https://www.privacyshield.gov/article?id=How-to-Submit-a-Complaint) you may be entitled to invoke binding arbitration when other dispute resolution procedures have been exhausted. 

Your data, including personal data that we collect from you, may be transferred to, stored at and processed by us and our affiliates and other third parties outside the country in which you reside, including, but not limited to the United States, where data protection and privacy regulations may not offer the same level of protection as in other parts of the world. By using our Services, you agree to this transfer, storing or processing. We will take all steps reasonably necessary to ensure that your data is treated securely and in accordance with this policy. 

We do not respond to Do Not Track Signals. If you have questions regarding our policy, please contact us [security@planning.center](mailto:security@planning.center) or  866-726-2730. 

Our services are intended for those over the age of legal consent. We do not knowingly collect or solicit any information from anyone under the age of 13. Our services and their respective features are not directed at children under the age of 13. 

Subject to the next paragraph, we ask that you not send us, and you do not disclose, any sensitive personal data (e.g., social security numbers, information related to racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, religion or other beliefs, health, biometrics or genetic characteristics, criminal background or trade union membership) on or through the Services or otherwise to us. 

If you send or disclose any sensitive personal data to us when you submit user-generated content to our Services, you consent to our processing and use of such sensitive personal data in accordance with this policy. If you do not consent to our processing and use of such sensitive personal data, you must not submit such user generated content to our Services. 

We may periodically update this policy. We will notify our users about significant changes to this Privacy Policy by sending a notice to the user’s primary email address listed with us, or by placing a prominent notice on our website. 

This policy's effective date is March 1, 2018. 

Please address any privacy related concerns to [privacy@planning.center](mailto:privacy@planning.center). 

Any questions about this Privacy Policy should be addressed to our support team at [support@planning.center](mailto:support@planning.center). 

Or by mail: 

Ministry Centered Technologies 

2790 Gateway Road

Carlsbad, CA 92009

U.S.A.
